in. Um, so I'm about to admit everyone
as usual. It does take a minute or so as
we admit everyone for everybody to be
in. Uh, for those who are joining, we
are starting the meeting and admitting
everybody who is in the waiting room.
Please be patient as it does usually
take a couple of minutes for everybody
to actually become live uh on the
meeting. Uh I am Dominic Zerlo and I am
the center director for department of
health center for medical cannabis and
psilocybin
and um welcome to the medical psilocybin
advisory board meeting. Uh the chair is
Ian Dunn and I will be turning the
meeting over to him in just a moment.
Just as a reminder this meeting is being
recorded and will be posted on our
website. So we do request that people
please ensure that their language is
appropriate for a public setting um as
we do post it for the public and
sometimes people who are of younger
years may be viewing it. So we want to
make sure language is appropriate. Uh on
a similar note um that is one of two
reasons why we do not have everybody on
video and in fact after this I will turn
my video off in just a moment and that
is for the other reason which is that
video seems to take up a lot of
bandwidth and for some of the people who
are joining from more remote areas or
areas where there's not as good of an
inter internet connection as there is in
other places the video takes up a lot of
bandwidth and causes them to drop off
the meeting and have to rejoin. And so
in order to try to keep that at a
minimum, we just have video turned on
for the board members and for some of
the staff, but we'll try to minimize
that as much as possible. And with that,
those are all of the announcements. I
will put uh the uh information for
contact in the chat in just a few
moments. Um but at this time, I will
turn it over to Ian. Ian, it is now your
meeting. And thank you everyone.
>> Good morning everyone. Thank you so much
for coming. I'm happy everyone can make
it. I'd like to call this meeting of the
medical psilocybin advisory board to
order. Today is March 20th, 2026, and
the time is 9:08 a.m. A quorum is
present. Um, so today's meeting, we're
just going to focus on program updates
and committee reports. No formal action
or votes are scheduled. The goal is just
to ensure alignment, transparency, and
shared understanding across the board as
implementation progresses. Uh but we
will begin with just a reminder
introduction if Johnny if you could call
the call the role of the board just so
we can introduce ourselves make sure
everyone remembers who we are.
>> Sounds good. All right. Um
All right.
We have uh Brenda Burkard present.
Uh Chris Pascus present. Dan Jennings
present. Despa present.
Chair Ian Dunn present. Larry Leman
present.
Um in place of uh Lana Donsense today uh
we have uh Kenan Ryan present.
And
uh
I believe that's all the board members.
>> Yes. Um, perfect. Well, what we can do
is go ahead and turn over to the
department for any um updates on what's
going on on their side.
>> Great. Thank you, Ian. Uh, this is
Dominic Zerlo again uh for those who may
be on the phone so you can know who's
speaking. Um and uh the the biggest
thing that we really have is we have two
uh announcements. I'll do one and then
we will have Jorge Gonzalez who is our
uh program manager do the second one.
The first one and um this is actually uh
thank you very much to all the work that
all the committees have been doing but
especially right now the propagation
committee because uh with the work their
work and with the outline that the board
approved uh in the last meeting we
actually are ready to release the draft
regulations and those will officially be
um announced in the New Mexico register.
on Tuesday and at that point they will
be put up on um both the Department of
Health website um or or well they will
be on the Department of Health website
for ability for people to view and to
provide start providing public comment
um and that will be announced both in
the New Mexico Register and in the
Albuquerque Journal. Um what will happen
at that point is there will be a 30-day
period for public comment and then on
April 24th
um starting at 9:00 a.m. we will be
having the public medical psilocybin
rules hearing. Now these rules are
around cultivation
and testing. So they're not a full set
of rules for all the different parts of
the psilocybin program. and they are
just the initial rules for cultivation
and testing. Um but again we would and
we invite people to read through the
review read through the rules and
regulations and see what thoughts ideas
they have and to present public comment
um with regard to it. Uh and so that's
our our big announcement and really
thanks a very much Chris Piscus as
chairing the the uh propagation
committee and all the work that he and
that committee have done and that
everybody else uh on this board has
actually done as well in relation to it.
Um some of that information has come
from the various committees and
different aspects of it. And so it's
just been uh it's just a really great
milestone to be able to say we're at
this point with uh with the with regard
to the rules. Um and uh so with that
I'll turn it on over to Jorge for his
announcement. Jorge.
>> Thank you Dominic. Thank you everyone.
Uh thank you uh members of the advisory
board do staff and and all attendees who
are been on the committee and attending
board meetings. Thank you for your
presence and good morning. Uh I am Jorge
Gonzalez. I am the medical psilocybin
program manager. Um and we recently
filled two positions which uh uh just
started and I will introduce them and
they'll say a few words about
themselves. First um we hired a senior
compliance officer and that is Leslie
Peterson. Leslie if you would introduce
yourself.
You're on mute.
Hi, thank you again. This is Leslie
Peterson. I'm honored and grateful to be
the senior compliance officer for the
medical psilocybin program. Um I'm
really excited to be part of a great
team with the department and the
advisory board to build and grow um the
medical psilocybin program. I do have um
years of experience uh ensuring
regulatory compliance with the
healthcare authority um income support
division, healthcare authority, division
of health improvement, CYFD, department
of workforce solutions, and now the
medical psilocybin program. Again, I'm
excited to build a strong foundation
with good habits to implement the
program per compliance to execute the
rules and regulations as determined by
the advisory board and the department.
Um, just want to utilize transparency,
accountability, proportionality, and
consistency. So, again, I'm very h happy
to be here. Thank you.
>> Happy to have you, Leslie. Thank you.
And now we also uh Leslie has been here
now three weeks and uh now next we have
uh we hired a environmental scientist uh
Cyrus Routtman and who is this is his
first week. Cyrus if you'd say a few
words please.
>> Good morning everybody. Uh yeah my name
is Cyrus Routman. I'm the new associate
environmental scientist for the medical
psilocybin program. Uh just want to echo
Leslie and saying that I'm really
excited to be here and to be working
with you all. It seems like a really
great team. Um, I'm formerly of the New
Mexico Scientific Laboratory, uh,
working on infectious disease and
pathogen sequencing. So, I'm really
excited to be over here now. Um, and
yeah, I'm just learning a lot and really
excited to be here. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Cyrus. Dominic, are there any
other updates? If not, Ian.
>> Uh, and I think we are back to Ian.
Thank you very much, Jorge.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dominic, Jorge, Leslie, and
um Thyrus. That was great. Since we did
not have a chance a little bit earlier,
if you could pull up the presentation
just so we can formally adopt the
agenda, that would be great.
>> It should be showing momentarily. Ian,
>> perfect. Here is the agenda for today.
Is there any objection to proceeding
with the agenda as distributed?
Hearing none, we will proceed. Um, so we
will go ahead and I'm going to ask
Johnny if you could call a role of the
committees. That way each of them can
give an update that would be great.
>> All right, sounds good. Um, Brenda,
would you like to go first?
Yes. Let me put my camera on. All right.
Thank you. I'm Brenda Burgard. I am the
chair for training and education for the
psilocent medical program. And uh thank
you for having me and uh thank you all
for being here.
Oh, and Ian, did um did you want like
brief updates um from everyone on their
committees or
>> Yeah. So, just what you have been
working on in general. It doesn't have
to be formal adoptions.
>> All right. Um so, um since I've been uh
this will be my I think my third meeting
coming up in April, I'm going to have a
guest speaker. Uh we're going to talk
about um uh what entails uh training for
education uh for um mainly people who
are already um uh practicing. Um,
however, uh, we're going to talk about
more of the,
uh, what other states have been doing as
far as training goes, um, how many
hours, but we're going to specifically
talk about, uh, what New Mexico, uh,
really needs as far as, um, training and
education go. Um uh we talked about last
time about reciprocity,
but next time we'll go over the um
the document uh briefly and then have my
guest guest speaker and uh then we're
going to go into
uh what people really want in the
document because last time I went over
it uh very briefly, but I think people
want to go go over a little bit more in
depth and then um I think I'll have my
guest speaker afterwards talk about uh
what training looks like um for New
Mexico. And then I think my third
meeting um I'm just waiting to hear back
from my other guest speaker to talk
about um training um for um more of the
uh people who are not licensed. So
that's still that's still being
discussed. So um that's what's going to
be discussed in the next meeting and you
know what the what competency looks like
for people.
>> Perfect. Thank you.
>> Awesome. Thanks Brenda. Um I think next
we'll go to Chris Piscus
for the propagation committee.
Good morning everyone. My name is Chris
Piscus. I'm the chair of the propagation
committee. Um, as
Dominic uh said, they are releasing the
um draft regulations of the propagation
committee's efforts on the 24th, so
Tuesday. And then there's going to be
the rules hearing on April 24th. Um,
super excited about that. We have had
two meetings where we started kind of
looking at those draft regulations or at
least parts of them. Um the
um permit applications for cultivators
and um labs portion and we also took a
look at uh the disciplinary actions
section recently and started kind of
making comments and and uh having some
community input on those sections. um
but larger
um
but we'll start looking at you know the
the hole on the 24th. So thank you all.
>> Awesome. Thanks Chris. Um and next uh
we'll go to Dan Jennings um with the
researching and continuous improvement
committee.
>> Great. Thank you very much. Appreciate
it. Uh we've had our third meeting for
this committee and really appreciate the
time and effort that they uh committee
members put into it. Uh we were able to
come to consensus on uh kind of a body
of research and uh best practices that
we look at. Uh so we have those kind of
published inside of our committee so
that we refer back to that and can make
changes to it as we need to. And we also
came to a consensus on uh a basic kind
of foundation for a data collection uh
and uh potential reporting system. So
again, it was just time to gather and to
show a workflow of the data that goes
between that. We've kind of put that on
pause to make any changes until we hear
more recommendations that come out of
different committees because those
committees will affect a lot when it
comes to education, training,
facilitators, propagation, etc. So, we
built the foundation and we're ready to
continue to add to that. Uh, we're going
to at our next meeting do a little bit
more work in more interstitial roles.
So, that way we'll have a uh a work
presentation discussion for the bulk of
our next uh meeting which will be April
10th at 900 a.m. And we have three
people who will be coming back to our
group to present on these three things.
One will be James Brown presenting on
challenging experiences or adverse
experiences uh the framework for
monitoring and scales threshold and
reporting limits and pathways. The other
will be Michelle Mirabindi who will
present on emergency preparedness uh
minimum standards for facilitators and
sites. And then we'll have Eileen Brewer
present on patient and community
education which will be core patient
education pre-intra and post session. uh
and it'll come up to more of a
convergence and next step at the end of
that so that we can decide what our next
uh workforce will be during that time
for our next meeting which will be May
8th. So again, April 20th, we'll have
those presentations. We'll make plans
for what we need to do in between and
come back again on May uh 8th to kind of
wrap that up. Thanks.
>> Awesome. Thank you, Dan. Um, next, uh,
we will go to Desba with the equity,
access, and cultural considerations
committee.
Okay, it does. I think something's funky
with your mic right now because it looks
like it's enabled, but I don't think
we're getting any sound.
I think she's saying she's going to
leave the meeting and then rejoin. Um
>> Okay.
>> So, do you want me to give dosage and
patient qualification while we're
waiting?
>> Yeah, sure.
>> Um so, patient qualification and safety
committee. Hi, my name is Ian Dunn. I am
the chair of that committee. Uh what we
have been working on is basically
contraindications, medication
interactions. Um we define treatment
resistant thresholds as two failed um
anti-depressants.
We looked at risk stratification um and
ensuring that patients are getting the
correct cultural support. And in terms
of those qualifying and safety issues,
we've packaged those up into a
recommendation. Um the only thing left
really for this committee that we need
to work on is general um stability
requirements. We need to work on um best
safety practices and um like things in
in the environment that you may not
consider like the number of emergency
exits and that kind of thing. Uh in
terms of the dosage administration and
cultural or clinical practice committee
um they have set up some dosage ranges
that can be prescribed. Um they have
worked are currently working through um
preparation sessions and all the
requirements for that. So there's been
really good work on both of them.
>> Awesome. Thanks Ian. And looks like
Desba just got back into the meeting.
Let's
>> Hi.
>> Hey. Yeah, we can hear you.
>> Okay.
Um so, hi, Celatee. Um our committee met
on the 11th most recently. Um we're
going to meet again on Tuesday.
Um
let's see. So, we basically went over
just our purpose and what we were trying
to focus in on. Um specifically, um a
couple of I sorry if I restated some
things that Dominic had said earlier. A
couple of certain um updates was that um
Governor um MLG signed um off on the
$630,000
appropriation for the equity fund. Um
and I think we also have some money
coming in for uh Larry for his um um
stuff, but he can announce that later.
Um and so we're still waiting to um get
some more formal uh meetings together
with the tribal leaison with the DO as
well as um the PBLO governors to get
more native and um the federally
recognized tribes here in New Mexico for
their input and or just to have um a
cons a meeting of the minds. Um, you
know, just to let everybody know where
where we're at. Um, especially because
the PBLO's here um have their own
sovereignty and we would like to be
building that relationship um within the
state and especially with what we're
going to be doing um with the
regulations and providing assistance if
you know what becomes the consensus. Um
so yeah, so we're going to be focusing
more on what that equity fund is going
to look like, who is going to be able to
utilize it um in the trials coming up um
next year um in the beginning of next
year um which will be you know, yay, yay
money. Um but we also had some
um minor concerns that do intersect with
the other committees which I will just
briefly point out in a bit but we also
were talking about uh tellaalth I know
that was something that was um
introduced earlier in the year but what
that actually really looks like when it
comes to and these I need to um
formalize or come to a consensus about
the language that I'm using and that
we're
um as far as the aspect of like when
tellahalth is going to be used for
screenings when tellahalth may or may
not be used for um I'm going to say
journeys um or use of the psilocybin
whether it's in a micro dose or if it's
in a you know actual bigger dose um and
then also for uh checking in in the
integration process um essentially so
we're looking at what those particular
look like. There's no there's been no
formal um decisions based on that. But
we are going to have to intersect with
IN's um committees as far as like what
that looks like as you know micro doing
during the use of uh psilocybin which
was brought out which was brought into
discussion by some of the facilitators
um or people who are you know trained in
this um facilitating
um
and also looking at you know ways that
the equity fund could be providing
support for accessorary
um accessory support such as providing
money for interpreters or child care,
elder care, travel accommodations for
rural patients and the time needed for
post- treatment recovery and
integration. Um so some of these are you
know potential barriers and we would
like to make sure that these things are
looked at um when it comes to
integrating that with um the rest of the
committees. Just really briefly, some of
the things that we brought up that may
or may not be intersecting with um some
of the other committees would be um as
to Brenda was talking about the
reciprocity of the facilitators. What
does that look like when there might be
out ofstate um with the with the border
communities um like Raton, you know, for
instance, or even Kirtland, Farmington,
those areas um you know, as we're
looking at into the future, what it
might look like if what are those
regulations if some other uh
facilitators outside of New Mexico are
being utilized in the state for rural
access? Um and then also to um Dan's um
uh committee, you know, what the
recording of prior use of psilocybin
might look like when bringing gathering
in data from people who may or
especially for minority communities may
or may not feel uh safe in providing
that kind of collection data. Um and
then I'm also interested in um
Dan's um the challenging experiences in
the education department which also kind
of intersects I feel with the equity and
access. So I just wanted to kind of
point those out. Other than that I think
that's where we kind of left off. Um and
just knowing that we need to start
thinking about the use of the equity
fund and what that might look like. Who
are we targeting for the use of those
for that money?
Awesome.
Thanks. Thanks, Despa. Um, and last,
we've got Larry with the end of life
care committee.
>> Good. Thanks. Hi, everybody. Um, we
we've been having a series of meetings
and ours been focused a lot on kind of
self-education right now as we try to,
you know, make make some decisions and
recommendations moving forward. So, our
last meeting we had a psychedelic
chaplain um talking. This afternoon we
actually have a meeting with a um
psychedelic deaf doula um who's going to
speaking and what we're trying to put a
lot of focus in is trying to understand
the the different potential roles here.
Other words, if there's two people
there, you know, is one of them going to
be in the psychedelic facilitator
therapist role? Is the other role
potentially a um you know, spiritual
role? You know, should everyone have
access to someone in the spiritual role?
Um and what would what would that
involve? So we're we're looking at those
and kind of going through a series of
understanding the different uh you know
the the different roles there and also
with an awareness that you know those
roles can be very different in different
communities. You know in some places it
might be a chaplain for the spiritual
role another place it may be a corandera
another place it may be you know you
know indigenous medicine person. So
looking at those looking at those um
issues. Um forthcoming we have um James
Brown is going to come on April 3rd and
talk about uh some of the
pharmarmacology issues that come up that
are more relevant to end of life. Um
April 17th we're going Jennifer Johnson
who I think is on the call is going to
talk some about the issues around um
hospice and perhaps with another
speaker. And we're we're building up
towards um a meeting which will either
be April 23rd or 24th. We're trying to
nail down the time by this afternoon.
Hopefully that's going to be a blended
meeting um that's going to be take place
in Albuquerque, but um the DO is getting
it set up that everybody from the state
will be able to participate and the goal
is to actually have some proposals to to
discuss that at that point in time.
other issues that have come up and I
know many of these touch across
different uh committees but I think
there's an understanding that um end of
life is going to be one of the most
important ones to look at the uh the
potential forum in home care many people
near end of life may not be um you know
able to make it into different settings
so looking at looking at how that issue
works
basically kind of where we're where
we're at now I guess we're We're hoping
that we'll be able to have some
proposals to bring back to the advisory
board um after the the late April
Inerson meeting.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Larry. Um and we'll
send it back to Ian.
>> Perfect. All right. So, it sounds like
the committees are all doing um good
work, which is great to hear from. Um I
do want to know uh Despa if you ever I
believe the tellahalth would fall under
it would either be patient qualification
and safety or dosage but I chair both of
them. So if you ever need a joint
committee um and just want to get
everyone together and then we can
discuss like all of that that would be
great. Um I think hearing everyone's
opinion would be really helpful for
that. Um but in terms of other business,
I think really what we want to kind of
establish here are our goals for the
next um package or framework that we
need to get through. So we have gotten
the propagation framework that'll be the
details will continue to be ironed out
by the propagation committee. Next, I
think we're going to need um like
training and education committee, not to
necessarily finish with all of their um
like the education they're going to be
providing, but with what kind of like
clinical lensure are people who are
going to recommend psilocybin going to
need? Um
you know, what who can certify
slashrecommends psilocybin and you know
who is going to be a facilitator? what
clinical um lensure do they need um and
that kind of thing. But I am open to
other comments. What do you guys think
is most important to work on next?
>> Uh Chris,
>> yeah, I just wanted to say I agree with
you that that the training and education
piece is probably the next priority. Um,
and I also just wanted to mention that I
got a little free time after propagation
is kind of wrapped up for now. So, if
anybody needs any help with anything,
let me know.
>> Perfect. Thank you.
All right. So, I say we should set a
goal to have our um at least what
lensure um is needed to fill each of the
roles. So um if you are on the
recommending side can it be NPs,
advanced practice pharmacists, nurse
practitioners, physicians assistants,
MDs, DOS, all that kind of fun stuff for
um facilitators. Do they need to be a
licensed social worker, clinical
counselor, or is this just kind of
someone um that's going to be working?
These are kind of the questions I had
for that committee. Um, so maybe by the
end of April, but we are still looking
at that. Larry had a comment
>> as we're looking at that. One thing
that's come up with the end of life
committee is is the families of end of
life that there's some fairly
specialized um, you know, training that
people should have that are working in
that role. And that may come up with
other committees as well. But I'm I'm
just maybe encouraging as you're looking
at the you know at the qualifications to
do that that we look at whether there's
specific education requirements that may
be needed for end of life or any of the
other diagnoses.
I would concur with that. Um especially
because we have um with end of life,
you're not only dealing with the
end of the life and the specifics that
come with that, but you're also going to
be dealing with transporting psilocybin
outside of an approved setting. So, I do
think that is incredibly important.
Brenda,
>> um, one thing that kept coming up was,
um, we're not really clear about all the
different,
uh, professions that are licensed or
certified.
And, uh, some people were saying, you
know, hey, is um, are is is the
education and training just for people
that are licensed now? what's licensing
going to look like for people that are
not licensed or certified?
And it kept coming back to, you know,
how many hours of training is is this
going to be? Um especially for people
that are, you know, already licensed
like doctors and nurses and therapists,
what's that going to look like? And so
that has to be discussed in further
detail, I think, in our next meeting. Um
I think what's been happening is there's
been uh a little bit of a
um from what I from what I get is that
other states are saying that you know
there has to be at least 150 hours or
120 hours of training but I'm looking at
that as from start to finish people who
like professionals that want to do this
work but don't have don't know anything
about it and that's what I'm looking at
and other people are talking about like
different tiers of education and what
that's going to look like. So, we're not
too clear. I think the public's not
clear about um what that's going to look
like. So, I'm hoping to address a lot of
that in the next meeting.
>> Perfect. Thank you. And Dominic,
>> thank you, Ian. And Brenda just
addressed a lot of what I was going to
say very well. One of the things that we
are doing from the department side is
creating lists of all the different
potential lensures that currently exist
going through all those making sure that
we're checking even in areas that might
not otherwise have been thought of
before and uh so ensuring that we have
that so we can help to address the exact
issues that Brenda is bringing up
because there are different thoughts
about how the training and the education
piece should be approached and um you
know and that's part of what I I think
it's been great in that committee quite
frankly is discussing exactly these
types of issues so that we ensure that
we have the best type of certification
for uh those providers and practitioners
that we can have and that it actually
results in patients having excellent
care um based upon their knowing that
their providers have the appropriate
levels of education and understanding
about psilocybin treatments. Anyway, but
thank you.
>> Thank you. Uh Larry had another comment.
>> Yeah. Uh it's related similar to how
Colorado's done this and I think it'd be
worth sharing who doesn't know. They
they have had some advanced pathways and
so if you're in the advanced pathway you
could potentially only need 50 hours of
training um which could focus on ethics
and and regulations. But I think what
they did, which I think honestly makes
sense, is is is not just grant people
like ours just because they're a nurse
or physician. And honestly, as a
physician, I'd say your your typical
physician knows next to nothing about
psilocybin. And so I'd be careful about
doing that. But what they did do, and
this this requires some thought, is give
um people who had worked in other
settings, potentially internationally,
potentially um what people might call
legacy uh keepers who worked there, and
they have them actually document the
number of hours that they worked. And
that could be relevant for both
indigenous or other legacy. But um I I
think there's some some value to um you
to learn that. I definitely agree that
150 hours for someone who's been in this
field in different ways, whether um you
know above or underground would be
excessive, but I would be careful about
just viewing a nurse or doctor as having
particularly special training for any of
this.
>> Thank you. And Desma.
Yeah. Yeah. I was just basically going
to echo just what um Larry was just
said, you know, as far as like the
legacy. Um you know, there have we we
all know that there are um lots of um
indigenous elders and wisdom keepers
that have been doing this work. You
know, it's been passed down to them from
their families. Um and we need to make
sure that we provide support for them as
well. Um, I do feel like, you know, just
to kind of have like an equity standing,
you know, that there should be some sort
of like
grandfathering in of the system, you
know, especially because I'm, you know,
a massage therapist. This is the thing
that I was looking for when it comes to,
you know, the reciprocity of like
different states and I know there's
different regulations, but it was just
that it was just to echo um what that
really looks like. Um, and uh I think
that was I think that was it. I think I
think that was it. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Um, and I just want to
reiterate like I wasn't saying these are
the people who should be allowed to
recommend. I was just saying like in
general we should figure out who we're
going to allow. Um, but yeah. No, I
completely agree with all of your points
that true. Most medical professionals
and I talk to many on a daily basis um
have very limited knowledge on
psilocybin. It's not taught in medical
schools. It is done primarily through
independent just looking through the
journals. Um, one thing that I would
suggest and I don't know if this has
been discussed in length in the
committee um but so what they do for
teachers actually is they give a
provisional license where you can work
practice have your class but um
and you know still get paid but it's
pending review of your principal until
they um
for them to issue your final license. We
could try something like that if we are
set hard on clinical hours. Um, if we're
not, then I definitely do recognize like
even if this system is new to what's
officially recognized, it's not a new
system. And so we should honor
experience from um
people who have been practicing even
when there are consequences on the other
end to help patients. So, um, yeah, uh,
Desbella had a question or a comment.
>> Yeah, and I think kind of to that point,
I know I'm I'm saying this also, you
know, because I know we're all on the
committee and Bren Brenda specifically.
Um, so I'm dressing I feel like Brenda
and yourself. Um,
you know, we can also I like the idea of
doing co-committes, so I'm I want to do
that with everybody. If if you have we
can kind of coordinate and having the a
co-committee joint committee, that would
be really awesome. Um but uh to that
point you know because I'm a massage
therapist I know that there is something
I haven't looked into it with the boards
of regulations you know there is
something about I think sooras
um in there being able to practice but
to your point I think that is definitely
there has to be somewhere where there's
an integrating of you know what in case
of an emergency those kinds of like a
baseline
uh kind of regulations I don't you know
even if this is where like the western
and the medical the western and and uh
indigenous
uh wisdom could possibly intersect is
you know CPR what does that look like
when it comes to trainings you know I
I've been doing CPR trainings like for
decades and you know every year it
changes um essentially but I think those
types of baseline understandings of what
to do those things are definitely
important when it comes to the
regulations whether it's a wisdom keeper
or a nurse or anybody else. And maybe
I'm just preaching to the choir, but I
just kind of wanted to say that, you
know, where where does the intersection
lie of these two different, I guess,
kind of mindsets. And also too, I know
that there are people um already working
on how do we get western medicine to
understand and be able to um get gain
some knowledge of what people have been
doing for centuries um with this
medicine because sometimes we're so
stuck in the way things are supposed to
be done, how they've been done, you
know, from this model, you know, what
can we learn from each other? And I
think that's um a place of reciprocity
and understanding that's important.
>> All right. And then so I'm going to ask
Brenda um how when do you think you
could have this the training and
education?
What's your goal completion date?
>> Oh. Uh well, when do you want to have it
done? That's my question.
I in an ideal world I would say end of
April. In a realistic world probably
sometime in May.
>> Um I think um
we well I think um from
the draft since the draft was um pretty
much complete on the first day. I think
what what um I may wind up doing is um
if I can have um um a couple maybe two
more meetings in May, two or three more
meetings in May if I possibly can just
to um nail down some things because I
think what what's happening is um people
are I I guess they they're not really
understanding
what all what we're doing as far as like
lensures go and all of that because it
is um a lot of different professions
that want to be recognized and be able
to practice along with the experience
that they have uh obtained either
underground or through certifications
through other institutions or other
education programs in other states. So,
um I think what we're going to try to do
is um you know, my guest speaker is
going to be Katherine Waro. I failed to
mention that in uh on April 10th. And I
think we're going to get a lot of
information just from um what she's
presenting there. Um I think what what's
kind of holding up um the idea is how
many hours of education
um uh with uh the lensure having kind of
a tier kind of thing where okay if
somebody's already licensed and has been
certified uh through let's say maps or
um maybe the these
from Pat which of the psychedelic um
association. Um so uh there's a couple
of different things that I think the
board uh needs to recognize from other
institutions what uh the DO is going to
accept as far as the education goes. So
I think um I think we just need to get a
list of all of those institutions which
I have I do have a list of that um that
the um do will recognize. So I think we
just need to kind of put it all out
there and um get it cinch cinched up as
much as we possibly can and and not get
hung up on
um how many hours. Um I think as far as
um the training goes uh there is uh
especially tailored for New Mexico um
it's it's there I think um a lot of
people who are already teachers I want
them to come forward in this next
meeting and um try to get this hammered
out as much as possible without getting
stuck on certain topics that seem to be
oh um not so much a banter back and
forth but um what's what's right for the
New Mexico and you know our our patients
too what's going to be safe and um uh be
able to be implemented. The other thing
is is that I think that
uh there
there seem to be like in our last
meeting other people from other other um
uh states uh I I think we're getting a
little bit nervous because we're moving
so quickly and uh when I was saying in
that last meeting about us running out
of time
um I it just seemed to me like uh maybe
The public was a little nervous about
how quickly we are moving. However,
there's and and I failed to say this, we
we shouldn't be reinventing the wheel
here. All that information is out there.
We just have to to um find what's going
to be appropriate for new New Mexico
clients and our practitioners. So that
being said, um you know, if uh and and
also too, you know, the legacy thing,
what what that's going to look like. Um
uh a we're lucky that everyone is very
very um knowledgeable and and sensitive
about
what what that will look like. And um I
think I opened it up that you know, hey,
having a just a another um model for
that and what that's going to look like.
Um uh yeah, there's safety. Um yes, like
Desba was saying, you know, CPR, you
know, basic things that you need to know
for safety could be um uh presented to
uh you know, the the tribes that are
wanting to be part of uh the the the
medical program here and you know, maybe
even having specific training just for
that and what that is going to look
like. So that in itself, there's a lot
of working parts here. I think if we get
something down that is
um uh equitable and fair for everyone
and um it's going to be a tall order,
but at least if we get something down on
paper, we'll be able to um at least have
something that we can find that is um
going to be at least um have that
training and education there and also to
have um it be as safe as possible for
our patients.
>> Perfect. So, um I appreciate all of your
thought into this. Um so, would
May
22nd be a good deadline?
Uh the 22nd that May 22nd
um
let's see um
I could we uh have it by May 29th
time here.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. May 29th.
>> Okay. The 29th. Okay.
And um on May 8th um if I could possibly
have an earlier time
on May uh like the 9 to 11 if if that's
possible.
Johnny.
>> Um, Brenda, the only issue with that, we
already have the research and continuous
improvement meeting is scheduled for
Friday, May 8th.
>> Okay.
>> From 9 to 11.
>> From 9 to 11. Okay. Is there
Okay.
Um, okay. Um,
all right. Okay. I'll I'll just keep
What is it from 1 to three
on that day? Okay. Okay.
All right. Thank you.
>> Perfect. And if you need any support or
if we can help out in any way, let us
know because you're not we're not like
sending you off alone in this.
>> Thank you. And of course um you know um
I invite everybody who can make it to
those meetings to um actually give their
support on this because um everybody's
an expert in their field and um I I
can't attend all meetings. I try to
attend as many as I can to you know keep
my ear to the ground and and and see how
that is all going to be um uh laid out.
especially um another thing that was um
a concern was like dosage, you know,
things like that. Uh and so uh I I think
that um there's there's a lot of
information here that is going to be um
laid out here in the next couple of
meetings.
>> Perfect. Well, thank you. Um, Chris had
a comment.
Oh, he put his hand down. Uh, Desma,
this is both to Brenda and Larry. I
mean, not Larry, sorry, excuse me,
Dominic and the um admins.
first to the admins. Um is it possible
that we can maybe get that um
uh meeting with the tribal on and
possibly I know I know trying to
coordinate everybody is like trying to
I know it's impossible but in theory
would it be possible to try to
coordinate something prior to within
within the month of April maybe um and
then that way we can maybe possibly join
join Brenda in a meeting on May 8th and
or um be able to have that input um for
helping to kind of at least just get
more of a consensus from the general
public. Cuz as much as you know we these
meetings are open and they are available
to the public and we have the the links
and stuff. um having that in like the
formal invitation of trying to actually
invite people to your house and come and
and join is sometimes not always easy to
get everybody's involvement. So, in
theory, I'm not sure if that's possible,
but that would be to me like a
possibility. And I don't know if that if
Brenda would be open to trying to see we
can get that going and or to have more
of like um
representation representation um at the
meeting so that we can help Brenda um
with any of that input is my thought.
>> Sure.
>> I appreciate that. Sorry.
>> Oh no. I was just going to say uh that's
just up to as far as the chairs of the
committee to determine what dates and uh
we can request that at that point. So
just need to let us know which dates you
would like to have that representation.
I can't guarantee it because I can't
speak on their behalf, but we will
definitely uh extend that out.
And Chris,
>> sorry I put the hand raise button down
instead of unmuting myself. Um, I was
just going to say if we, you know, and I
do agree that we're rushing things a lot
in these committees and in this process,
but if we have a deadline of the end of
May for our training, that leaves seven
months without, you know, the rules
um, propagate, you know, being
promulgated and all of that for people
to get training
um, which is not a lot of time. So,
and in addition to that, like I think we
need to start stacking our
our deadlines with the other committees
as well because if we continue to do one
at a time, we're we're just not going to
make our deadlines here for trying to
get people treated this this coming
January.
Uh, Desba.
>> Um, to that note, I guess maybe we
should probably make it clearer, and it
wasn't clear to me. Um, what kind of
trainings? Cuz what I'm hearing from
Chris, and I could be wrong, is, you
know, that there's the there's the
propagation side of the training, or are
you specifically talking about like the
facilitator training? because I'm seeing
that like we could possibly have the
facilitator training kind of implemented
and like looking at, but we could also
have then what I would see is
potentially Chris's concern is what does
the training look like when it comes to
propagation? I'm not sure if there was
if that's the case or if I'm
misunderstanding something. No, I don't
think anybody like the micologists
already know how to grow their mushrooms
and so, you know, they're getting their
rules posted out and can learn how to
follow those in time, but there doesn't
need specific training on that. Um, I
I'm talking about
who needs what training needs to be
decided fairly quickly if we want to
meet our time frame. Um and that is in
regards to our facilitators, what
clinician training looks like and all of
that.
>> Yeah. Cuz I think what he was trying to
get to is if we end up requiring
clinical hours, there isn't going to be
enough time for the rules to get
finalized and for all of that. But I
think there would still be enough time
to get the people that are interested
even with an adoption in May. It would
just be cutting it close. Uh Dominic,
>> thank you Ian. And and just a couple of
points on this is one thing to remember
is and this is something that has come
up in the education and training
committee as well is with the December
time frame it doesn't mean that
everybody is going to necessarily be
trained at that point. That's not
necessarily what is needed. We need to
have some individuals who have training
and who have that. One of the big points
that's come up multiple times and in in
different committees is ensuring that
there is a process for grandfathering in
So people who have already gone through
the time and expense of getting
trainings in other states and so with
this kind of a time frame and looking at
the end of May as far as for the
committee to have their recommendations
that will still work because even with
the regulatory process it's going to
give enough time at a minimum even if
we're not able to train additional new
individuals in that time frame although
some people might be able to get trained
trained uh you know even if we didn't
start trainings in New Mexico until
November and December they'd be trained
in that spring early summer time frame
but we have a lot of people who are
already trained as facilitators who have
the experience who have the knowledge
and understanding as long as we have
clear um you know grandfather or
reciprocity whichever way you want to
call it with those trainings that have
already been authorized by both Colorado
and Oregon. One of the main points has
been that we need to ensure there is an
additional module for New Mexico and
from the Department of Health standpoint
we have already said we will create that
specific module so that will fall to our
team and so we can have that created and
be doing that in parallel with the
process for the rules and regulations so
that once the rules and regulations are
ready and once they've been promulgated
accepted and promulgated We'll be able
to have that module ready fairly quickly
for people to be able to complete it who
have already gotten their training and
have already done practices in other or
practicums rather in other states and so
be ready to be able to do this. So that
is definitely a part of this and a piece
of it because again remember what we're
looking at and the aim of the program
it's starting. It's not going to be a
full program. We're not going to have
everybody all set at that point. It's
just that by that point we'll we'll have
already had uh propagators or
cultivators having been established.
We'll have some um patients that are in
the program. We'll have providers who
are already trained or who are uh have
the reciprocity from the other states.
So that's why we look at this time frame
as being uh still a reasonable time
frame because we can have those parts
and pieces. Will it be everything for
the full program? Will we have um
practitioners in every part of the
state? No, not at that point. But we
will have a start and be able to work
and see even at that point where some of
the gaps are so that by the statutory
deadline we have a much more full and
complete program. And so that's part of
the idea on this. I just want to help
reassure people that we are actually on
a good time frame and things are
happening in parallel. They're not
happening just one after the other
because as Brenda mentioned there's
already been a lot of work done on the
education and training part. So it's not
as though we're just doing one piece at
a time. It's just a question of which
pieces do we focus on and once we finish
some what are the next ones to focus
upon. And so this next set is the
provider uh education and the patient um
portion as well as far as the
requirements. And then the next piece
after that are what exactly are the
locations and the requirements and the
locations. But all of this is happening
in not just um in sequence but in
parallel. So I hope that helps to
clarify some of it and helps to ease
some of the concerns I'm hearing about
people being nervous about it or feeling
that it's rushed. We're we're trying to
ensure that we're doing this fully uh
you know as completely as we can with
those sort of um you know safety
mechanisms in place and the
understanding that this is just the
beginning. This is not the end. It's
just the beginning.
And with that I I'll pass. I see the
next person on is Larry. Larry.
>> Yeah. Thanks Tom. And as usual you've
you've answered most of my questions
raiser. Thank you for that update. I
just like to bring up two issues. Um,
one of them is I mean given proximity, I
think Colorado is actually where people
in New Mexico tend to be going right now
to get trained. Um, we're actually with
our UNM research, we're doing that.
We're sending people up there. So, we
have an idea about the timing that's
involved. Um, you know, people um at
this point probably the soonest people
get into programs there would be in the
fall, but that would have them ready to
go by March and 27. So, it's not not too
far off there. One important thing I
think to think about sooner rather than
later is um the pathway to do practicums
here in um in New Mexico. Like when
we're sending people up there, we're
actually having them do the 150 hours
but not actually doing the practicum
with the thought that they would
probably uh be able to do that here at
some point in time. And you know, so I'm
just put a little pitch there to have
the committees see if we can fasttrack
the the practicum so that can be
approved well before we can probably
have a full program in the state.
>> Thank you, Larry. That has been a point
that has been brought up and discussed a
little bit.
>> Thank you.
>> And I think Brenda has her hand up next.
Oh, Brenda, you're on mute.
>> So, you guys are touching on everything
I want to concentrate on. So, uh, just
to be clear, Dominic, um, so
would the Department of Health, um, uh,
be working on that module for, uh,
people that are already trained or, um,
would you like for my committee to to
work on that in the next meeting?
>> So, we we'll work on creating it. The
part that we will need to know from the
committee itself is what are the main
topics or curriculum that the committee
feels would be most appropriate for
people who have been trained in other
states and then the department will
create that that module so to speak.
>> Okay. And um uh because I've been uh you
know I get out there I talk to other
people and and that kind of thing. So um
uh there are like um many people like
myself that have been trained by maps
and and that kind of thing. Um we were
also discussing like a refresher course
uh and um I think that would be really
good because um as you know MAPS was um
because of MDMA not passing you know uh
for uh the federal government
recognizing that. I think that would be
a really great thing to have and
probably roll that out. Uh probably as
soon as June um uh the beginning of July
and maybe just having a uh brief uh
six-hour course with the the main six to
eight hour course with the main topics
on that and and um maybe integrate a
little practicum in there as well. Um I
know I just went through training with
EMDR and they're doing it in two parts.
Uh Friday, Saturday and Sunday one month
and then in and again the second part is
in May um uh Friday, Saturday and Sunday
and uh there's a practicum inside those
modules. So, um I'm kind of stealing
something from already. I'm kind of
working from and I think that would make
um the rest of everyone that's already
trained have it uh for New Mexico and
and be ready to go. Uh because I really
would like to have that training uh up
and running as soon as possible and
everybody in between. I've been telling
people, yeah, go to Colorado, go go
ahead, keep going with your training
because if you're going to the
institutions that are um you know, at
least the five uh or the the at least
the 10 top um training programs that are
out there that have um been recognized
in uh by other states. I think that
would be a great way to to um get the in
between people ready because there may
be some people that will be ready by
December and they're going to there's
going to be a lot of overlap with all of
this and also too um uh have another um
module uh and maybe Desba and I can and
uh talk about that in in a meeting
together. uh as long as the do can can
uh schedule that for us, I think that
would be a a a really good part to kind
of just get it in there and and start um
you know running with all of this and
get this going and and because I think
one of the main important things is
safety, safety, safety and also respect
um with all of this too. So that's all I
got to say
>> and thank you Brenda and and you're
hitting exactly on the kinds of things
we're talking about with having that
module is making sure that it does some
of that refreshing and also to help with
from things such as cultural competency
and having that aspect. The only thing I
would say is from a time frame is
looking a little bit more like
Septemberish give or take a little and
we can see what that time frame is as we
get the rules for the education and
training. And the main reason I say that
is because we'll want to develop and
actually take the time and ensure that
we're doing it correctly. As you said,
collaboration with Desba and some of the
other individuals um on the on the um
equity committee with education and with
for example the research as well as you
know some of the different specialties
that Larry has kind of brought up for
example. And so to make sure that we're
doing that in a good comprehensive way,
I would just say give us that little bit
of extra time to create those aspects of
the module. Um and uh just because I my
concern would be is if we say we're
getting all these requirements in May,
uh it's going to take a couple months
for us to actually develop it into a a
really good educational and refresher
type module. So I would say if give us
till about September, give or take a
little, but we can talk a little bit
about that. And I think what this does
is let people know these are the kinds
of things that we're doing that we want
to ensure are there to help also with
the concerns about this being rushed
that there are plans we do want to make
sure that things are done well safety in
mind um and of course ensuring that
people have the appropriate training and
the connections because I think that's
very much important that people
understand those connections anyway so
thank you definitely I think we're in
the same wavelength overall Um, Despa,
you are next with your hand up.
>> Yeah. And I just wanted to kind of um
reiterate, you know, all the things that
you were saying about, you know, what is
what what are the minimums to get the
door open and it's not, you know, how
we're how we're going to continue just
on that
time, you know, just on those
regulations just as they are. You know,
it's going to be evolving and we're, you
know, try how do we how do we continue
to move it forward? But then also um you
know for the for instance you know we're
sending all these people to Colorado or
you know the certifications in Oregon I
was a part of one of the trainings and I
didn't get to complete it the one that
was in Colorado of Nuropa. Um and you
know by this time I would have already
been certified. It would just be the
practicum. they weren't like able to do
that for, you know, the people in
Colorado or in Oregon. It because there
wasn't one in place yet because it
depended on your place of residency. So
those things are really important for
anyone who who has already done the
training. I think they're still looking
at the practicums in their home state
where they were where they're residing.
Um and and then also
um God, my brain just completely lost
what I was going to say. Um but you
know, you said your next thing would be
like the requirements for the locations
and the permitting and what that what
that looks like. Um,
and so I'm I'm I'm looking forward to
being able to get input from more
people. And I I feel like you know the
psilocybin community is in my mind is I
want to say it's small and maybe that's
where a lot of like the fear is coming
from because it's like what we are able
to know but like the general public the
people that we're trying to reach and
who may not know what these what you
know what this really is. It's providing
them an opportunity to be able to have
these things in place and and maybe
that's part of it. Okay, I remember what
I was going to say. But it's just like
that fear that we have that it's it's
not going to be enough. You know what we
do have what we already have that really
it's hard to rely on the underground
because there still is like with you
know there is still a fear. um but
reaching out to our own smaller
organizations, the the um the knowledge
keepers who are there. I think there's
some things going on in northern New
Mexico. Um you know, we need to make
sure that they their trainings that they
have that they are offering already
within the state. we need to fi you know
go fishing out and find them and make
sure that they have the support so that
they are not fearful of of anything
right so because all these places in
Colorado Oregon New York they have money
behind them to back them for whatever
reasons to be able to provide the
research but we also need to make sure
that we're providing that support for
the people that are here in New Mexico
already doing that work as well and it's
hard because you know this is why we
need everybody to to talk more about it
is as much moving past that fear to talk
more about it openly and I'm I'm seeing
it I'm seeing a lot more um but I feel
like maybe that's part of it there's a
lot of fear in you know we're not um
doing things right but it's mostly it's
like we we have so much knowledge and we
need to go make sure that we are
representing that knowledge and that
we're allowing it to be able to breathe
um and bringing all of that information
here and to talk about it But it it's
already here. It's already happening and
we just need to make sure that we're not
leaving them behind while we're looking
in Colorado and Oregon and elsewhere.
>> Thank you, Desba. Uh Brenda is next.
Um I I I agree about the fear um part of
it because I think what could be um a
roadblock is that um especially people
who already have licenses in their
profession.
The fear is is that okay, what kind of
protection do they have if they're
practicing with this medicine
and um it's still not, you know,
decriminalized? You know, how do we get
the message out or, you know, uh legal
for for use? And um will New Mexico
recognize um that in itself that you
know this medicine can be used? Um so I
think that I've heard it once or twice a
couple people go no you know I don't
want to do this because you know I I I'm
really trust that we'll be able to be
protected. I could lose my license.
So there's that there's that fear there.
Um
uh because we live in a society too that
you know let's say you have um a
therapist that's administering you know
the the medication and uh they have
someone that
that I guess wants to um hurt them in
some way and so they report them and
make a false report and then you know
they're having to shut down their clinic
or their um you know ability to
practice. So um I hear a little bit of
that. You know what's the DO going to do
about that? Um and if we are going to be
insured, how much is that insurance
going to be? How much are the licenser
going to be? So I get a lot of those
kinds of questions and I go I don't know
exactly. So they're not willing to take
the risk to um even do this even with
people who are certified
>> and Larry. Thank you so much, Brenda.
>> Yeah, thank you Brenda. Um I just want
to address the issue of like DA license
and um and what you bring up. Um I
there's a participating in an end of
life psychedelics training and uh
Katherine Tucker who's probably a
leading lawyer um in this area is
presenting. She presented that um New
Mexico may be in a different situation
than Colorado um Colorado and Oregon
because it did come through as a
legislative initiative that there may
actually be an added protection um um
based on your like a medical profession
following the their um their state law.
I don't totally understand that it was
complex. She was giving a whole complex
legal thing and I know we also do have
some lawyers that attend our call
sometimes. and Victoria. But um it
looked like that would be worth looking
into because um I mean there there's
multiple needs for people feeling
protected. Um one is simply um you know
if people are writing letters that
saying this person does have PTSD or
they do have um treatment resistant
depression for that and then then
there's the issue of people actually who
have DEA license being facilitators. But
I think it may be helpful to talk to
Tucker or get some other opinion because
there may be ways that things can be
coded, put into our codes that are more
protective. Now, honestly, no one's
particularly excited about like, well,
the DEA can come arrest you, but but we
have an out. I mean, so people really
want to be they don't want to get there,
but but it may be useful information,
Brenda, to to deal with some of what
you're hearing from providers.
I mean, in a similar vein, most
providers are scared, even if they're
prescribing controlled substances that
are legal at the federal level, they
often are are honestly just
fear-mongered by the DEA. So, I don't
think there's much we can do on that
side. But I do know that um SB219 said
that our state level medical boards or
board of nursing will not take adverse
action due to lawful participation in
the psilocybin uh medical psilocybin
program. So I believe our state has
taken efforts to try to reduce the
impact but I mean we've done what we can
in in that sense.
and dead stuff.
>> Sorry. Um Um I'm only laughing because I
just keep raising my hand. Um yeah, I
and what I'm hearing though and is
especially is just like what maybe is
the misinformation
that continues to be forwarded? Um and
then what are the differences you know
for New Mexico like we're all discussing
here you know those aspects but um I
think we're in a age right now where we
have so much information
that and this is just the general
collective human consciousness that
where we're going with everything
there's just so much information and
even with the idea of like AI is it AI
or is it not you know we're not able to
discern
what the misinformation might be. And I
feel like if there's anything of a
collective effort coming from the
Department of Health and and otherwise,
you know, I know you're doing a great
job of providing that information out
there. Um, but it just seems to me that
we need to kind of figure out what that
baseline is for what this really means.
I know within the smaller psilocybin
community, we are pretty much all, you
know, know the differences between why
like the legislation is important that
it was implemented versus it being on
the ballot. But again, we're dealing
with like the general public and you
know, we're dealing with the rural
communities. And if it's even difficult
right now within the age of so much
information flooding you and coming at
you,
it's important that we provide what that
baseline is and knowing that people
have, you know, specific rights or like
where they can go to and and and how to
provide that. And I feel like that also
moves into how do we work with the
tribes, right? Again, that was just been
the thing. It's like we have this
information, we have these
opportunities. How can we help you help
yourselves? And there is agency when we
feel like we are empowered to know what
our options are and that that this
medicine which used to be an option to
our relatives and ancestors years ago
without any, you know,
repercussions that now that we're in
this age that there was kind of taken
away. But now that it's being offered
back and what that looks like and moving
past that fear is the knowledge. Um so I
just I just wanted to say that um you
know what does it look like when we are
offering
what our ability to move forward with
this and and and it's and it's it can be
very scary for you know anybody even if
people know in theory this is the right
thing. I know that this is going to help
me. There still is this like the the
world that we're living in, right? That
is just how do we move past that? How
can we help support our general public,
our citizens in New Mexico to be able to
have that agency and that empowerment to
know that this is an option for them and
and and for the you know the I was I
said something in our committee. It's
like if we can just offer support for
one person to help change their life and
move it forward. And I probably know
like a lot of us have have experienced
that that change and that shift. We're
changing and we're shifting the
communities and how many more impacts
and what that looks like. So if we can
just be able to provide that support for
that one person in that one community,
then that changes their family that
changes in that area and that's how we
can move forward. But we also have to
provide them the the right kind of
baseline information that will help them
move in their in their capacity.
>> Well, I really appreciate your thoughts
on that. Is there any more discussion to
be had?
>> I'm seeing none. So, let us go ahead and
plan our next meeting.
Ian, sorry. We did have uh one other
point. Um and Desba referred to it a
little earlier. Um but it's the the part
about the funding and I'm pleased to be
able to say that uh we do also have
Senator Jeff Steinborn who is here on
the meeting. So um uh for those who are
not aware, we um through the legislative
process this year, Senator Steinborn was
a huge advocate for the program and
especially with regard to research and
with the equity fund and was uh
instrumental and uh really was able to
help to ensure that there was an
allocation of $630,000
for the equity fund and an additional
$300,000 for research. um that is going
directly to UNM for the research side.
And so uh thanks to him, we're going to
really be able and his efforts as well
as the other legislators who were
involved in that. And I'll let him speak
on that that aspect, but um really
thanks to him for uh us being able to
provide some of the things that we will
be providing down the road and ensuring
that equity and access around the state.
And so with that, um, Senator Steinborn,
if you'd like to say a few words.
>> Sure. Hey everybody. Good morning. It's
great to be with you and great to be
back from the legislative session.
That's for sure. Um, yeah. So really
excited that we were able to uh
appropriate these funds for the program
and to make sure we start off strong and
you know that there's funding there in
the equity fund when the program
launches as well as uh continued money
for research on these kind of cutting
edge topics that are included in our
program uh for uh for Dr. Layman there
at UN M. So just I wanted to just share
a few notes about both uh funds. So the
uh equity fund the 630,000 was was money
we appropriated directly to the equity
fund. The equity fund you know I think
now that there's funding at some point
it's going to be good to look at what
the law says about that fund and what it
can be used for. But also I want to
point out it is what we call a
non-reverting fund which is really good.
Those are important words because it
means that it doesn't have to be used in
one fiscal year. In fact, it doesn't it
basically gets to be it gets to be used
until it runs out and and it does not
revert back to the state, does not
revert back to the general fund unless
the legislature were to at some point
sweep those funds, which it can do,
which we sometimes do during dire fiscal
times. We we take money from unspent
funds, but um we're not anywhere near
that situation. So, I want to point out
it's non-reverting, but also I kind of
the flip side of that is it's one-time
money. It's money that was funded out of
discretionary legislative funds that
we're able to appropriate. It's not part
of the base budget. And so,
you know, I would say use it
judiciously. um we don't have to be you
know too chintzy about how it's spent
but at the same time I would say
understand that it's not something
that's automatically uh replenishing
every year um you know it's always
dependent upon surplus legislative money
that can change with you know economies
pandemics so just be aware of that it's
it's it's it's a great pot of money but
it's also not inf it's also not
infinite. Um I think part of our ability
to appropriate future money for this
fund will depend upon the economy, the
availability of funds, legislators
support individually
um who are willing to fund it if we
don't get it through the budget process
and uh
and then also I think the data that we
collect and the successes that we have
from it, you know, will will be I think
important for the whole program, but how
we're documenting what we're doing and
and the and the success we're seeing
from so that we can help share those
stories to help get more support in the
future. So anyway, I just wanted to
share those notes about that. Now, the
money that um was secured for Dr.
Leman's program, even though the law has
a research fund in it, we have found
that um with the excellent program with
Dr. Leman, this may not always be the
case, but this was the case when we
started the program in this year that we
that it was speedier to get the funding
directly to Dr. Layman and appropriate
directly to his program so that we don't
have to then have the department have to
go through their bureaucratic process of
doing an RFP and slow everything down.
So, so the money was appropriate
directly to the UNM psychedelic assisted
therapy research program and uh it was
really cool that we were able to do that
and so that generally does have to be
used within a couple years and uh but
the legislature can also what we call
reauthorize it and extend the use of it
so it's it can be flexible but hopefully
that will be really good for Larry and
um end of life anxiety research
specifically what what we're all wanting
to uh put more money into. Finally,
Dominic, I just want to give a shout out
to um
to Denali Wilson who was just super
helpful uh being able to be boots on the
ground there at the legislative session
and she and I kind of working members
and you know and then and Chris and um
other um other folks who were able to
come up to the session to help advocate.
Ian was there um hanging out with me on
the floor for a day which was really
cool. and all of you or any of you are
welcome anytime to do that as well. Uh
but um yeah, so it was just a great team
effort and of course uh it was a
bipartisan group of legislators in the
House and the Senate that both gave
their discretionary funds to this
project. So um that's a really cool
story in and of itself. It's very
bipartisan, continues to be and we are
all rooting for your success. So that's
all I have and thank you all for the
good work.
>> Thanks.
>> Thank you. Thank you so much, Senator
Steinborn. We definitely appreciate all
of your support and of the other
legislators as well. And so, thank you.
Uh, and so on to Ian.
>> Thank you, Senator Steinbornne, for that
um just kind of breakdown of what you
did. Uh, as you know, you went to UT
Austin, motto is what starts here
changes the world, and I'm glad you took
that to heart. Uh, Desbuff,
>> um, I had a question um for Senator
Seinborn and then also um a second
question. When you say the fiscal year,
so when does the money specifically drop
in the bank for use? And and so for how
long is that? And then just really
quickly, you mentioned the data
collection and documented success. And I
wanted to kind of throw this question
out to Ian and Dominic and um Dan. Is
this what an opportunity to have like a
joint um
uh committee or just making sure that we
take note that this is something that
for the equity access research that this
is a place of of of joint movement or
consensus. So for so the fiscal year and
then the data collection
Yeah, thanks. Dominic, I think just put
it in the chat. The the fiscal year for
the state of New Mexico when we pass
budget starts July 1st. So that's, you
know, generally when things um funds
become available and all that good
stuff.
Certainly in the case of the equity
fund, it'll be there before the program
starts. So, but it'll be there starting
July 1 technically.
>> Um
>> this year or that's the question mostly
of this year.
>> Of this year. Yeah. Yeah.
>> So then the end date, which doesn't have
an end date, we could still then be used
like it's available July, but then so
when the trials start January 1st, then
we still have
>> the rest of until it runs out is what
I'm hearing.
>> Yep. Mhm. Until it runs out. Yep. It's
non what they call non-reverting. So it
does otherwise otherwise when we do a
lot of appropriations, it does get
reverted if if we don't. But with these
funds we put in that language so that
they can hang on to it and use it. Yeah.
So,
>> okay.
>> Good good question. Yeah.
>> And then to kind of respond to your
question for me and Dominic, I would say
the equity fund largely falls within the
equity access and cultural
considerations committee. Um, one of the
things that like I would definitely take
into consideration as discussion goes on
is that um, how much is going to be
available via tellahalth and how much
isn't because that might change. Are we
allocating PDM to people in um,
why can I not think of it like Raton to
travel to Albuquerque or Santa Fe or um,
like kind of what are we doing there?
are we doing it by income levels? Um,
and those kind of things can be taken
into consideration once we have like
what more of the program developed. But
we definitely should start making um
recommendations on who should qualify
especially when we're seeing those first
um
you know where the first industries pop
up.
All right. Is there any other
discussion?
So,
with the
training and education not being done
until the end of May, we could push our
meeting back to there or we could meet
again. I would be okay meeting again in
May. Um, what do you guys prefer?
>> I'm sorry. Did you mean May or April
or did we already have the April meeting
set up?
>> Um, so we did not have an April meeting.
The only reason I skipped April was
because training and education was going
to be largely using that um month. We
could meet in April. I would just say
probably
May give us a little bit more time.
>> Yeah. No, I I think I at least for me
personally, like I had mentioned, it
would be nice to maybe possibly do joint
meetings with other committees if they
are available and I can probably see
when they have agendas. And I'm not
trying to push my agenda onto your
agenda, but I just, you know, I'm
offering that um to kind of be more
formalized even though like even if
we're popping up into meetings and kind
of voicing things, um a more formalized,
hey, you know, equity and access is
joining training this month or whatever.
Yeah. So, um we can
So, did you want the next medical
psilocybin advisory board meeting to be
in April or were you saying you wanted
your joint in April and then in May?
Okay, cool. So, how does everyone feel
about
Well, we could do May 29th and then
review the training and education. Does
that sound good to everyone?
So on our calendar, Ian, just so that
you know, I'm the Department of Health
that uh May 29th is open.
>> Okay. So 9:00 a.m. at on May 29th.
Everyone good with that?
>> I I may have to miss that. I'm I'm out
of town that day.
>> Yeah, I'm on a a practicum that day,
too. Can we can we switch it to a
different day?
>> Yeah. Uh, do you want to do May 15th? We
won't have time for the training and
education, but I'm sure we could have um
I'm sure other committees will have
stuff that we can work on.
>> That works for me.
>> And that is open from the department
standpoint as well.
>> All right. May 15th at 9:00 a.m.
Perfect. Oh, Chris had a comment. Sorry,
I did not see your hand.
>> No, I think it I was just commenting on
the scheduling. So, and I just jumped
in. Sorry.
>> Yeah, no worries. No worries. Um, all
right. So, that works. So, can we move
to public comment?
>> All right. Sounds good. Um, yes. And if
you'd like to um comment right now, um
if you raise your hand, there is a uh
icon of a hand that says raise at the
top left part of the banner in um Teams,
you can go ahead and click that and then
I can enable mic privileges after that.
And um if you'd like to submit a public
comment um to
uh our email as well, if you have um
wonder thoughts or or would just prefer
to do it that way, you can email the um
medical.silocybin
email at uh dooh.nm.gov.
All righty. Seeing no hands, um I'm
going to go ahead and adjourn this
meeting. Adjourn this meeting. Thank you
guys so much for showing up and having
discussion with me today. I really
appreciated it. Um again, if you guys
would like to submit public comment
through email medical.silocybin
dooh.nm.gov
And um we will accept them until 5:00
p.m. on Monday.
>> That's correct.
>> Perfect. All righty. Well, thank you
guys all so much for coming and have a
great rest of your day and a great
weekend.
>> Thank you everyone.